i want to say something
to welcome kenny best regular
and he'll be elvin benkel
thank you yes so unfortunately
evelyn couldn't be here today
and while i'm start talking i'll start to share
my screen so yes evelyn is struck ill this morning
so unfortunately she cannot come so uh all the
best uh to her and um let me get the chat up as
well so if you have questions or comments during
during this talk you can i'll see the chat and
maybe i can react to it so today will be a talk
about autonomy is that what we really want and
i'm really humbled to be back at ddd taiwan for
the second year and i really like it unfortunately
not in taiwan my wife would have really loved it
she is addicted to bubble tea she really wants to
go there one day so hopefully next year we'll
go there so talking about that let me share a
personal story first so me and my wife recently
moved houses it was around in the neighborhood and
yeah we move our main goal is to live close by
her parents also my parents live close for us
it's important to have family close to us and the
added benefit is since my mother-in-law comes from
asia she gives us a lot of food which is also
important to us but we moved houses recently and
this earlier this year and if you look at autonomy
you would think well i have a house now i can do
whatever i want on that house which unfortunately
is not the case if you look at my garden here in
the back right and there's a carport you would say
well let's just add more garden to the carport and
i have a bigger garden well unfortunately
this neighborhood got designed 10 years ago
there was an architect along with the with the
authorities here and they say in the contract
that this part this carport needs to be able to
hold one car why because if everyone would do do
this in the neighborhood there won't be enough
car spaces left so you know if you talk about
autonomy are we now really autonomy with our own
house no so if we would have moved to well a more
rural area in the netherlands then of
course maybe we'll have more autonomy
but in this case um is autonomy what we really
want because in this case for us it's close to
live close to our family now and of course i
have cats so are we truly always autonomous
well we have a cat door here right so we need to
abide by our cats because well eventually they're
they're in control usually so but to describe and
move on with autonomy we need to well define it
a bit so autonomy as described by mr pink as
the urge to direct one's own life without the
ability to control what when and how we work and
how and who we work with will never be completely
motivated to complete the task so that's autonomy
right and within the domain driven design
scene autonomy is when you look at the batman
context pattern right autonomy is a big thing
but we're lacking mastery and purpose there and
we're so focused on that autonomy so mr pink in
his book drive describes autonomy as direct one's
own life now are we could we actually ever be
completely autonomous and completely control and
have the ability to control what when and how we
work now if we will ask if philosophers and if
romeo would watch this he would agree then we're
born free but the first thing is our parents
right our parents control us and we follow the
instruction retaining only in some cases but this
is a big philosophical question that we're not
going into today because that will take weeks
maybe months maybe years maybe never to solve
so autonomy in here is uh well there's
an illusion of now if you look at the
definition it's the quality of state of
being self-government especially the right of
self-government the territory was granted autonomy
so if you look at the dictionary autonomous sound
like self-directing freeman and especially moral
independence personal autonomy now if you look
at my house where i live do i have the autonomy
to do that no i haven't because i'm part of a
village here so i'm not autonomous right and
and that's the thing with autonomy if we look at
software development and here you have uh jape
and mark saying i hate the word autonomy right
it's individuating i have no right to make my
own decisions that's what we hear i have the
right to make my own rules when we look at domain
driven design and software developer is that truly
what we really want that autonomy of course we
want some self-organization self-government but
we truly want autonomy because in this case in my
opinion autonomy can be compulsive right a goal on
its own instead of a means to an end but autonomy
in isolation is not enough it's part of a bigger
context like my home i'm living in now right it's
part of a bitter context i have neighbors i have
i have people living in this village so i
cannot really do what i want and the same goes
for software development right in software
development i'm building software with my
team preferably and of course i cannot do
what i want and that's the polarity here that
we're going to talk about the polarity is between
isolation and connectedness right us uh me versus
we and autonomy is on that skill and every time
we need to decide and balance these two things
right so autonomy is that bulk concept that we
use as we please but the concept needs granularity
it means different things on different
levels well we're doing ddd workshop and we
face the importance of language and meaning
all the time right so we want to be exact
on the word that we use what does it mean
and it's no different for autonomy when we're
going to use it autonomy defines boundary on
multiple level and that's why we're here today
we want to dig into this concept see what it means
on different levels tell stories about what we've
seen in organization and teams and how autonomy
can be misused misinterpreted and be a risk for
the record we're not saying autonomy is bad it
might come across that way now but that's not the
case autonomy is brilliant when we all know within
our relevant power what it means and applies so we
will share some learnings and observation while
we evelyn's not here so i'll take over for her
and that we think we might help you in
defining these powers more effectively
so where do we actually need autonomy lots
of teams and people state that we want to be
self-organizing and or self-steering both marked
as autonomous but there's a difference here
you can be self-organizing i can self-organize
my house but it still requires steering right the
government here scares me it happens all the time
teams asking for vision from leadership please
don't interfere with how do we do things here but
let us know what the end goal is where you want to
go with this company so the first question is
where do we need and we want autonomy and how
much do we want it right what's the skill uh and
that comes into defining boundaries well we're
in a domain design conference and boundaries are
like one of the core concepts in the window and
these boundaries are hard to define when we stick
with the bulk concept of autonomy that's why we
dive into different levels with pitfalls and
opportunities but first let's visualize this
polarity between connectedness and of course the
other one which is the part and the whole right
so this is what we're going to talk about autonomy
is part of the skill between that part and a whole
in system thinking you have it right part and a
whole and what connects me with these things and
this is a lemnis cut right it's a it has both
upsides and downsides between the two yeah so
if you look at the part the part is the eye it's
the more autonomy way right you have uniqueness
but you always also have isolation now if you look
at the whole like being part of a whole being part
of a team you have connectedness but the danger
there is also sameness right there's no uniqueness
anymore in it and this is what we need to manage
this is what we're gonna go into now first thing
um also we we talk a lot about polarities with
hin it's a friend of ours and she has this nice
fun fact internet so so the lemny scott you just
saw in the middle right comes from the latin word
lemny scotus what does it mean so i give you
10 seconds is it round corners decorated with
hanging records or the devil's curse so use the
chat and i will see maybe someone has an answer
so let's see so it's a ground corners decorated
with hanging arguments or the devil curse so
anyone has an id i don't see anything in the
chat so i'll just say it's decorated with
hanging rhythms some people say it might
be the developed skirt spotted songs so
let's continue with the talk so today we're
gonna talk or i'm gonna talk about four levels of
autonomy yeah so the first level is autonomy and
code i'm going to clearly go inside code because
there's this lenny scott as well and then we go
to teams then we go between teams and then we go
into organization and if you look at domain-driven
design this is the full area domain-driven design
and tilts right it's the whole thing we do for
software so let's go to autonomy and code and
there's no silver bullets and golden hammers
that's what i would like to start with right
there's no one way of doing things because it's
that balance that tight balance that we need
so when i started coding i came into a team and
well proper unit testing was a thing we needed to
do proper unit testing but back then i saw this
unit test as well i have a java class in this
in in this case and then i create one unit test
for that class right it's always one on one one
class one unit test and what happened is that at
some point i find myself creating a lot of mocking
stubbing faking in all these unit tests and that's
only one strategy we picked right one on one an
isolated strategy so we isolated these all there
but there was no connectness between the classes
and the classes should actually represent units
where there's a form of autonomy and isolation
so martin fowler recently put out this blog post
right about test shapes and there you see it in in
in the book by j fields working effectively with
unit tests you see you have two types of tests you
have the social tests which are often the tested
unit relies on other unit systems behavior right
but i'm not stubbing it away i'm using it as
a whole unit a unit of work a unit test so i'm
using everything and i'm not using any monks now
the other one here is the solitary test that's
the strategy i used at the start right i have
one unit one class i stop and prefer to isolate
that tested unit and you see i mocked it away
and both of these has side effects right think
about the connectedness and isolation again and
we need to manage that there's no one approach
here that you can take take the approach that
solves the purpose and a good friend of mine
thomas pierrot he he says and the goal
here is to look at the outside in and have
proper acceptance test coarse-grained connected
unit tests right which is in the middle
and we might go find grades in the unit test
which are more solitary tests right but first
of all we go here and then in the end we might
do some contract test integration test between
our systems but as long as our acceptance tests
which are core grade unit tests work i'm fine now
where do we do this on well we're in domain driven
design community so if you look at the bounded
context it has a model for a purpose it is a unit
of consistent language we can do tests on here
right tests are also part of that bounded context
the bounded context language is represented in
the tests as well as in the code as well as what
we speak etc etc so how would that look is let's
say in the middle and i'm using a hexagonal or
ports an adaptor's architecture but in the middle
i have my domain model represented in code right
with objects in this case i'm an object-oriented
programmer you can do this functional as well it
doesn't really matter but the model is exposed
in code and what you see is at the top i have
my acceptance test and my acceptance test will
run on the port that goes inside the domain and
then i mock away every object or every connection
that's outside my domain model i'll mock that away
and now my acceptance scenario will test my full
domain and these are really the
sociable tests from the highest level
and when we go deeper you'll see that oh maybe
this one object here is really complex so i need
to create a solitary test and maybe that object is
really complex so i'll make a solitary test right
and maybe these three objects together is
the aggregate so i also make a social more
sociable tester right so as you see there's no
one strategy for me the goal is to have this
acceptance scenario run against my domain model
and that's my end goal as long as these succeed
it's fine but of course this has long feedback
that's the downside of it so i need to go in depth
so how would that look in our polarity map again
here you see the solitary test on the left you see
the sociable test on the right and there you can
say well the good thing about the solitary test i
tested in isolation fast feedback on failure but
if i go to the negative it's cascading changes
on mocks and stubs and the loss of unit of work
cohesiveness right so we can fix that with the
sociable tests which are coherent no mocking or
coupler but failure of bug in other classes and
slower feedback of failure right balance we need
to constantly balance these two and i'll later
describe how we can balance this right but as you
can see on the top my goal is to feeling secure to
change the code and my fear is cascading changes
so as you can see there's no one way and if we
look at autonomy again right autonomy sits now in
the middle how can i get these two into balance
now then let's go to autonomy and teams and
there's this individual and interaction over
processes and tools right an individual can
be autonomous and so can be a team a team is
a collection of individuals that can either work
as one autonomous team or as a group of autonomous
individuals well right language and meanings
would be crucial the nuance here is crucial
so i have we have to break it to you but we are
in the end all hurt animals that really really
need to be liked by other people and get that
confirmation it's been described in cultural
anthropology a lot in sociology and as soon
as we start talking about relationships and
things get personal we get uncomfortable
that's the problem we might feel unsafe because
rejection is around the corner that's why we
love our precise technical problems so much right
i don't have to deal with other people but
the thing here is isolation in a person is
is not good for a person right we identify
ourselves through others so we need to have
that heard feeling we need to have that feeling
that we belong to someone there's actually
a lot of tests one test that went on in
the united states when they still isolate
people in prison right when they had that behavior
and they figure out it didn't work they didn't
self-reflect because they couldn't reflect
because in order to reflect you need the other
right you need that connectiveness so that's the
paradox we want to be autonomous but at the same
time we want to belong to a group of people when
we act as a group of autonomous individuals and
don't feel like a hurt we lose that feeling of
belonging right and in perceived individual and
autonomy and perceived team monument what
works for any team differs that's really
context depending on a team same as all my bounded
contacts are context dependents and what works
depends on that but they have to be on the same
page because otherwise things can get messy and we
can turn into a dictatorship right so imagine you
have a nice development team working on a product
everyone's doing their job but there's one
person that seems to call all the shots
it can be a tech lead that can be the person
that's the longest there uh it's probably the
person with the most knowledge that person has
undocumented knowledge most likely and that's a
problem this person can be brilliant and building
the best product but let's use rigs right so the
netherlands they call it the bus factor i would
now rather like to call the lottery factor so a
colleague told me that so if this person would win
the lottery person is gone from a team what now
but on the other hand you know it can also be nice
to have a lead developer making decisions again
we are hurt animals and sometimes we like the dog
making the decision for us guide us right guide us
to our home so what we have here is an autonomous
team with one autonomous individual that has most
power which can lead to undesired behavior and
that can grow because we don't want to lose that
person we get dependent on the person right you
get the downside of the laminate scat you know
the polarity and if we don't switch and we don't
manage that it becomes worse or worse and worse
a person can work in isolation because we assume
the person is doing the right thing meanwhile
we you have an autonomous team where stuff is
lurking beneath the surface this can grow and
grow and eventually explode leadership needs to
turn that ship around right it's leadership that
need to manage that again we need to do some sense
making to see where are we at and we need to be
able to talk about it define the boundaries what
do we expect of each other in terms of domains
teams but most importantly about what it means in
terms of behavior as an individual and as a member
so because autonomy is a bulk concept it can be
misused like said dictatorship is a potential risk
but we've also seen autonomy being used as
an excuse as a means to shift the blame to
someone else example an organization read about
autonomous teams want to do it maybe microservice
is right and there's your first flag don't just
copy-paste stuff because it works for someone else
watch on one of our previous talk to talk about
that and about cargo calling and the copy haste
based hell that's mutating but one very important
note here is that culture is crucial surprise
within this particular organization there was fear
fear of being held accountable distrust no room
for failure and a lot of pressure so for the teams
autonomy sounded pretty good because it would get
some of the pressure off or so they assumed
for management autonomy sounded good because
they interpreted that as full responsibility with
the teams which was good for their cover your ass
culture right it didn't look too long for this
to clash deadlines miss no clear communication
and lessons learned moving toward autonomy
because it works somewhere else or because
it might help you cover your ass won't bring you
anything sounds trivial but this happens you need
someone to expose this behavior and consequences
in the case of organization it was us doing that
instead of focusing on autonomy we start with
building trust and create a shared meaning
we need a shared meaning we need a shared
purpose and this is what drive mr pink always
also said right we need a purpose and well what do
you know domain driven design and abounded context
can help you with that because of down at context
it's a model for a specific purpose we know this
is what we do it for this is what we build it for
for this customer we're building this model right
and then we can use things like context mapping
and domain design to see the connectedness with
other teams which we're going to talk about
that later and within something nick tuna the
ddd crew up uh is this bounded context canvas
where you can describe that description right
this is really nice because now together with the
team we collaboratively model our purpose together
and we see what are our inbound and outbound
communication and this is how we stay connected
and define these bounded context problems but it's
not only about boundaries uh it's also the way
we develop our work and one thing i see in in
each phase of each uh sorts of programming and
now you'll see load code popping up is that
people have a problem here it says application
teams grows it slows down because multiple
developers compete to change the same code
first of all i don't see that as a problem i see
that as oh maybe we need to talk together and see
how this fit together but they see it as a problem
and that's the thing right it's not a problem
so what do they do they actually deliver a
different pace so they're going to do branching
nice you got a branch you get a branch everyone
gets a branch well do you hear the isolation
coming in here right just working your
isolated thing on your own purpose
and you'll lose connection there's no balance
here so what you'll see in that in that thing
is that the feedback is late right so this
is git flow by the way and as you can see
as if if this is the main line you see there's
no real feedback here because this happened and
you know long feedback and that can cause to
some cost fallacy well i've been working on
this course a really long time right and someone
else would say well yeah but that's not what we
discussed i mean i thought it would be a different
design and connected differently okay let's just
take some duct tape and fix that and we'll call it
technical debt which it's not it's craft there's
slow feedback he wasn't connected to show that
again on the polarity map you'll see right the
branch gives you freedom individual creativity
but you have loss of cohesive mental models well
you know bounded context is a shared model so
we're losing that the longer we are on the branch
but the positive effect of the trunk based so
let's say we do only mainline development is care
for the whole shared mental model team effort but
we have excessive conformity so trunk base people
see trunk based as being only on the
trunk which is not you can use branches
and how would we check that is look when we
observe our team and we see people competing to
just change the same code maybe we need to start
pairing and lobbying right and at some point you
can find signals that you're too long on that main
line then we go back and find the branch right
balance there's no one way to do it don't don't go
on and this is not trunk based development that's
defined right in trunk based development
you can do branching it's not about only
committing on the mainline code you could do
branching but don't take one approach over the
other so don't always take the trunk based
development or i mean mainline commits and
don't always take the branch implements balance
it choose every time what you're gonna need
so then to my favorite topic which is autonomy
between teams i already talked about it with
the context map so how does my team relate to the
other and and people think well let's do bounded
contacts microservices so we have autonomy and
and there again we can go towards isolation again
yeah so in this case autonomy between teams
microservices and can go on to a lot more
can la lead to the ivory towers to the
silos that's not what we want so one
thing that happened a few years ago is this book
called team topology that come out right and team
topology really loves domain driven design while
team topology is about teams and about fast flow
organizing business and technology for fast flow
of their teams domain-driven design is about
autonomy in models right and these really work
well together because these teams for fast
flow will be owners of these models and the
models has relationship with each other and
that's what i'm going to talk about really quickly
is if you look at what they describe the fourth
fundamental team topology is you have these
perhaps a platform team you don't always need
a platform team but let's say you need but in the
end it's about this middle team the stream aligned
team right the stream aligned team is picking
up value for the customer and releasing it in a
fast flow and because they cannot do that always
by themselves because there's this thing called
cognitive load because that's what we should think
about right about limiting the size of software
services and product to the cognitive load that
the team can handle so the stream align team
could be in a lot of complexity well one thing
we'll talk i'll talk about later is the enabling
team right where you need some new technology
some new testing framework perhaps or a new
database technology then another team can help
you uh periodically to implement that but a team
can also be accountable for one big ball of mud
bounded context right and that can be complex
and they will put on another team and that's what
we don't want we don't want two teams working on
the same well context in that way because they
use different languages and that's what we don't
want so what do we do because we cannot put
one team on it because the cognitive load is
too high now again domain driven design gives
can give you an answer here eric evan described
this there's no one way of doing it we don't all
want bounded context with anti-corruption layers
on it and and just be isolated no in this case
what we could start doing is form a partnership
clearly define two bounded contacts within that
big ball of mud see if we can do that and set up a
cooperative relationship between the two teams and
these teams establish a process for coordinating
planning of development so you lose a bit of
autonomy here but you decrease the cognitive
load yeah and and that's what domain-driven design
is all about it's about trade-offs none of these
strategic patterns are by default bad they just
are right even the confirmation pattern people say
the confirmation strategic pattern can be a bad
thing it doesn't have to be it's about trade-offs
so don't think about the um utopia that every
bounded context is autonomous no that's not
what it is um there's these several patterns eric
kevin's clearly discussed and there's more after
that you can use and it's all about that balance
and i was already talking about that enabling team
right so we have to stream align team and they
can afford partnership with other streamlined
teams and they need a platform team maybe maybe
there's a complicated subsystem team this like
for instance we need some data science for uh
doing much doing our stream align team but then we
go to this enabling team right i i already tell
you about the enabling team but the thing about
enabling teams there's a danger here if we
just have an enabling team like for instance
a test team or a architectural team right and
they act we need to manage that they actively be
avoid becoming ivory towers of knowledge dictating
technical choices for other teams to follow this
is what we usually see as a pattern we have a
architectural team dictating technical choices
or a testing team in isolation dictating this and
here's this brilliant comic agile right that says
there's one team is constantly
developing huge number of features
well nobody is using it anymore we got to stay
connected an architectural team in isolation is
that ivory tower team they're not helping teams
an enabling team is a supporting team there to
help the other teams and they have an end date
what's the purpose of that enabling team right
because what happens usually if we stay in
that isolation right they have freedom they
can go fast it's nice work ahead of new technology
they have uniqueness but if they stay too long at
isolation they have lots of equality isolation
they will become selfish but they will also get
the downside of the collaboration right they
themselves will get high cognitive load they
self will guess excessive conformity and sameness
and this is how a polarity works as well if you
stay too long in one polarity you get the bat of
the boat yeah and you're becoming that tower of
babel instead of customer centric and enabling
teams customer here are the stream align teams
and then let's talk about my second favorite
topic after branching is of course the skilled
agile frameworks which has their place
and which can be implemented correctly
but what i see here is a lot of isolation
patterns right so we need to manage this we
need to manage the connectiveness and the
relationship through these polarity modes
so autonomy organization so let's talk about this
last level right autonomy in an organization which
is again a continuous negotiation and this sounds
this sounds somewhat paradox right an autonomous
organization but this organization can consist of
autonomous teams individuals or maybe there's no
autonomy of all the thing is it's a continuous
negotiation what do we mean with autonomy
in organization where do we need provide
autonomy and what does it bring what does
autonomy mean for the way we collaborate what's
my role all very important question to consider
in this context right and let's start with vision
boundaries for both let's start about remembering
the thing we said about boundaries and vision in
the beginning of the talk define the boundaries
in the shape of a vision is what the leader team
teams should do the vision comes from leadership
what i hear when there's need for efficient within
team is in fact a call for boundary tell us what
the boundaries are in which we can decide how to
work this is also a job for a software architect
right we define the boundaries constraints for
innovation we don't decide how people do it so if
you want something to be done as a leader you set
the boundaries this is what i want and what do you
need for it so basically that's what leadership
should do right so people saying if we all have
autonomous teams we don't need leadership anymore
yes we do they manage these polarities and there's
a difference between uh the old school machiavelli
leaders right it's command and control it's ends
justify the means and what you see nowadays
a shift towards the collaborative leadership
right they set boundaries they set constraint they
make sure that the autonomous teams stay connected
with each other and this is leadership
this is middle management and this is uh
architects that might sit in between the teams and
i say in between the teams and not above the teams
because they're equal right and that's where our
topic is it's not a free pass it still requires
conversation right that's what we need we need
someone to create these connectedness and create
this conversation and we cannot stress enough
better collaboration direct communication is
not behavior if we want to expect something from
a team it needs to be observable right it needs to
say what outcome not output not tasks what outcome
can i expect from you uh well evelyn can talk a
lot about that season 4 is not here but she will
discuss that in a different talk later on what
exactly is behavior and how could we do
it so direct communication is not behavior
so who calls a shot i already told you that with
autonomy it can be confusing who gets to call the
shot which makes a decision which decision are
you allowed to make that's a hard question in
general but especially when there's autonomous
team it has to be made explicit which again is
a continuous negotiation boundaries this is this
is i got from the brilliant root milan and from j
bloom boundaries you create in negotiation yeah
it's a continuous negotiation there are no hard
boundaries usually they're not really hard it's
they're not fixed it's a continuous negotiation
if a boundary is fixed it's called a wall it's
not a boundary anymore so if you agree about
what autonomy means what you can expect from each
other and where the boundaries are you can also
determine who gets to make the decision who is
responsible for what eventually leadership calls
a shot obviously ranking and budgets but there
have to be that continuous negotiation with the
teams and people in the organization it's up to
leadership to collaborate on that thing right
collaborate leadership that's the thing we need if
we have autonomous teams we cannot have a a person
on top who do a machiavelli type of dictator
leadership they don't match unfortunately it's a
negotiation it's a skill now we gave them autonomy
and why aren't they doing anything with it right
and that's the frustration on most leadership
teams they're like we gave him that so why is
no one taking ownership and responsibility i asked
him to turn around that question what can you do
to help them take that ownership because it's
not like a you say well here's your ownership
goal that person also needs to be able to feel
okay to take that ownership right so that's the
question you should have asked to the the team do
you want ownership how do you want it again here
you see the negotiation right and this polarity
map will help you it's that task of the leadership
to make sure and manage these polarities of
autonomy and connectiveness and isolation right
so what's holding them that what they're afraid
of which risks do you see and that's collaborative
leadership right it's setting visions it's setting
this is where we want to go with the company what
do you need for it how do we set the boundaries
how do we set the structure together that works
for you again please don't copy-paste any spotify
model that doesn't exist anyway what does the
team need which boundaries and that's context for
sending don't come with the mature maturity model
maturity model learning is not linear it's
context dependent as we know in domain driven
design that's why we have to monitor contacts so
when there's autonomy everywhere do we still need
managers i already tell you managers we still
need them but they can exist in several roles
or forums that's again depending on your company
but i believe middle management is a crucial role
for starting this strategy right higher
management is about option middle management
is about strategy jay bloom really described
this well if you have a football team you have
the people above on the top they set
options but really who sets the strategy is
the coach right it's the middle manager sort of
saying that's how we should perceive it as well
there needs to be shift and they are in the middle
they have a hard job but managers still exist they
need to change their behavior as well from a
machiavelli style to a collaborative style so
how would that look like in in a polarity map so
j bloom actually doesn't call it agency he calls
it or autonomy he calls it agency that's what we
want right it's the balance between decentralized
decision and centralized decision and if we don't
balance these two then we get into indecisiveness
so centralized decision means empowering to the
group group can coordinate group active group
can actively decide and everyone feels included
that's centralized decision by a manager right
but the problem here is is that we can have queues
we can be dependent on this decision we have lack
of individual accountability no creativity
or spontaneously and disempowering to the
individual so we also want to have decentralized
decisions and again it's a it's a lemnis god
right which is empowering the individually it's
spontaneous and it's individual acting decisively
but the problem with this central decision is
that the group cannot coordinate they get fear
of missing out and burn off consequences so we
need that middle management with sort of like
a team topology style managing these polarities
managing the connectiveness between the team we
need to have software architects either in the
team as an as a virtual team together working
on that contacts map how do the models relate to
each other how does the autonomy in the team come
together right and one thing one thing to be aware
of is that patterns of autonomy and isolation are
fractile if you have isolated patches at the top
you will find them in the bottom as well they
go and cascade down to your organization so
if you see a isolated pattern inside the team
probably what you will see is that the managers
are isolation there's no feedback this is what i
usually find weird in this organization is that
a middle manager doesn't get any feedback from
the teams end of the year performance there's
no feedback from teams and for me that's weird
because the middle manager is there to set
strategies constraints and vision collaboratively
with the team so who could decide that they're
doing their job correctly it's mostly in my
opinion the team and of course their leadership
did they help create that vision of the company
so autonomy is that what we really really want
well we need to define and negotiate boundaries
continuously and we need to manage the polarities
and that's the end of the talk i hope you enjoyed
and we always say please leave the judging to the
cats the left ones are mine as you saw before
these are my cats and unfortunately evelyn is
here but she'll be happy that her cat is
brilliantly displayed on this talk again
as we always do so we have a twitter account
both of us please feel free to dm us or tweet us
we have an email we have a website and if you
want to contact us let us know thank you very
much for having me here so far and hopefully there
are some questions i can answer them thank you
okay thank you very much and thank
you on your sharing and our audience
have some questions in slido so i need
to share my screen wait a moment yeah
okay so kenny can can you see my screen yeah i can
see it okay the first question is can you explain
more about the social technical because
i think it is very abstracted concept
yeah so i don't consider myself the expert on
social technical i know uh a few people who are so
this is my explanation social technical considered
and please follow trond or j bloom and root milan
they can explain this a lot better but here's my
view on it usually what you see in companies is
that we only take account the technical so the way
i describe it let's say if you work in the office
and if you're back at the office again due to
corona we live inside a or we might work inside a
open office plan right so we all work in one
open office and if i go to companies and i see
them using this and that's a technical design
right that's the technical design of the open
office plan it's technically it's correct we
can put everyone there technically brilliant
but when we look at the social part which is the
which is the uh which is actually two parts is
the cognitive part and which is the social
part which is a difference you'll see that
how does the interaction go so they tried to use
this technical design to improve communication
but they saw it work at someone else now they
put it inside their company and what you'll see
is that at most open office spaces actually the
the the everything went down except the costs
right so the communication goes down because
we all have these nice headphones on because
we're all getting too much noise and cognitive
load right there's too much cognition going on
i get too much inside so social it goes down again
and these two interact with each other as you will
see in his open office plan now the open office
plan works because people collaboratively designed
them so where it worked they designed that
together so there's a brilliant talk by joe wright
at lean agile scotland talking about the history
of it and there it worked why because they took
the social account and the social is more of like
towards the culture part the cognition so they
looked what are your needs what are your social
needs and what's the behavior inside here and
let's collaboratively decide designed open office
space there it worked and then you saw other
companies copy paste in that because they
saw it improved technically it improved
the communication it improved blah blah blah so
they thought okay let's technically move it away
as a design in my company but they neglected the
social part and the same goes inside inside your
software development as an architect right if you
develop these autonomous system or microservices
you need to take into account the social part
within domain-driven design you see that the
strategic patterns are really social patterns
most of them right the partnership i talked about
that's really a social pattern how do we
interact with each other and usually we
just take in account okay let's just split these
software in part boundaries but we don't take in
account what does that happen to the culture
the team dynamics that's why team topology the
strategic patterns get more important now doesn't
need to say that the tactical isn't important they
need to be in balance so i hope that answers the
question this is how i see it but please there's
multiple people who who can talk about this in
the scene and i always start at the root milan
uh c is already i don't know how long in
the architecture world and sees a brilliant
explainer okay thank you for your experience and
the second question is do you think the level of
autonomy should be given depends on people's
majority but will that slow down
people's growth to become measures
yeah so here's again it's the polarity right
what can i what can my team do now and that's
an open discussion with the team right this is
what the purpose is we want to grow towards fear
where do you feel comfortable with taking autonomy
here right so autonomy you can give it to a team
but it also means that the team wants to have
that autonomy some people are afraid maybe to
get that autonomy but if you keep that stable
that that balance stable yes people won't grow
to become mature so that's only the the skill you
want to constantly manage as a manager right or as
a architect that's the polarity map so that's the
continuous improvement that you can embed in your
software development flow is okay where can we get
more autonomy and what do we need for it a good
a good thing maturity mapping it's called so
usually what we do is have a maturity model in
our learning but you can also do maturity mapping
which is based on worldly mapping and there you
can go context dependent how can we grow as
a where's the boundaries and how can we grow
as a as a team towards that more maturity right
but context dependent for our team so it can be
that one person has all the information about
that new uh about that new technology let's
say we do surface there's one person who's
brilliant at it but the rest not okay what
strategy will we take now to make sure other
people will do it so bearing mobbing and then
four weeks later you do it again or two weeks
later and you constantly keep sense making to
see how is it going now and how can we change
now so it's a it's not a static concept it's team
dynamic heidi heinfeld has a brilliant book about
team dynamics it's ever evolved it's not static
thank you for your answer and the next question is
how can we distinguish systems that have full
anonymity from those with particular anonymities
wow that's a really good question i need to think
about so how can the skin which is another full
autonomy from so it depends right first of all do
you want to have full autonomy and what does it
mean so for me i rather have agency if i get a job
i can fulfill it myself i can have the mastery of
purpose to do it myself that's what mr pink
talks about and if someone couldn't do that
and meet someone else then it's partial autonomy
and the strategic patterns can help there indeed
to map these out right what's the level of
maturity and is that okay or i mean what's
the level of autonomy and is that okay in this
given context for instance if i'm working in
a core model or domain model right i might want
to have more autonomy because i need to iterate
on that model a lot if i'm in a supportive domain
model maybe i'm okay with having less autonomy so
that would be the first question and i'm okay
with a with a more tight partnership between
teams because i don't have to go that fast
in that parts of the software structure so
i would do probably the too long and read do
some contacts mapping on the current system
and then map the strategic patterns on them and
see and these strategic patterns are on a scale of
autonomy themselves right so for
for instance the confirmation
pattern is like low autonomy the
anti-corruption layer is a bit higher
autonomy but there's a different scale as
well that's how i would do it context method
okay thank you very much and then the final
question is anonymous coding more or less anatomy
well there's the balance again uh and that's
the conversation you need to have with you in
your team right so usually what i do is we
pick up a new for instance a user story or
or something new i start with the connectiveness
right i start let's do maybe some mob
programming this morning let's let's figure
out together how we want to design this
then we mop that and and while we're mobbing
we're creating a shared mindset and connectiveness
but you know uh we cannot maintain that for a
long time it's the tight balance again so what
i do at some point people are clear
enough and they say okay you can do this
you can do that and i can do this everyone
will code but never work on their own branch
they will just keep committing to the same uh
main branch then so everyone stays connected
so people were saying how about code reviews right
they say i need to go on a branch because i need
to have a pr for me a review is continuous so
if people will just commit on the main line
then i if i start developing and i want to
commit on mainline i need to pull their commits
i see what they did if i see something that that
is like oh this is not what i expected i i will go
back and talk to them again and that's the lemony
scot right so what are the signals that you are
going towards isolation or towards too much
uh sameness and that's the balance you need to
talk to as a team in that polarity map so look at
polarity mapping me he and evelyn talked about it
on the event store so i'll share that blog post
later and start doing that with your team so
ins you get that trigger oh this is
not what i expect let's pair up again